Sam Gejdenson Papers 2001.0008
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Sam Gejdenson Papers
undated, 1911-2001
2001.0008
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
236.0 Linear feet
Congressional records of Sam Gejdenson, U.S. Representative from Connecticut's 2nd Congressional district. The papers contain records spanning Gejdenson's twenty years in office. The papers include newspaper clippings on subjects ranging from veterans issues and the Groton submarine base, to Six Flags and tourism in Connecticut. Gejdenson's papers also include press releases concerning the environment, Electric Boat, and the Soviet Union's treatment of Jews.
Gejdenson, Sam.
Biographical
Samuel "Sam" Gejdenson was born to two Holocaust survivors on May 20, 1948, at a Displaced Persons Camp in Eschwege, Germany. His mother, a Lithuanian Jew, and his father, a Belarussian Jew, met in the camp following World War II. Gejdenson later moved with his parents to Bozrah, Connecticut, where they engaged in dairy farming. Gejdenson attended Mitchell College following high school, receiving an Associates degree before attending the University of Connecticut. After receiving his Bachelor's degree from UConn in 1970, Gejdenson began work for the FAI Trading Company before becoming the president of the Montessori School in Norwich, Connecticut shortly thereafter.
Gejdenson began his politcal career as the chairman for the Bozrah Town Committee, and was elected to the Connecticut General Assembly in 1974. He would serve the people of Bozrah until 1978, leaving after two terms to take a position in the administration of Connecticut Governor Ella T. Grasso. In 1980 Gejdenson became the first child of Holocaust survivors to be elected to the United States House of Representatives, representing Connecticut's 2nd Congressional district as a Democrat. Gejdenson served the people of eastern Connecticut in Congress until 2000 when he was defeated for reelection by Repbulican, Rob Simmons.
During his tenure in Congress Gejdenson participated as co-chairman of the Democratic Task Force on Retirement Security and was the Senior Democrat on the Committee on International Relations. He also served as a member of the Committee on Interior and Insular Affairs, the Joint Committee on the Organization of Congress, the Joint Library Committee, the Committee on House Administration, and various other task forces. As the senior Democrat on the House International Relations Committee, Gejdenson worked to promote the exportation of U.S. made products, to further the causes of human rights and peace throughout the world, and ensure that American trade policy was reflective of American workers' rights and the furtherance of environmental protection.
During his time in office Gejdenson became known for his advocacy for children, senior citizens, and working families, and fought to make college more affordable for working class families. He was an advocate of modernizing technology in schools, enhancing retirement security for the elderly, and promoted the exportation of American made products. He has also become known for his efforts to stop human trafficking throughout the world and for his efforts to enhance international understanding of human rights and democracy.
Gejdenson currently runs and operates his own trading company based in Branford, Connecticut; Sam Gejdenson International.
Scope and Content
Congressional records of Sam Gejdenson, U.S. Representative from Connecticut's 2nd Congressional district. The papers are organized in archival boxes containing records spanning Gejdenson's twenty years in office. The papers include newspaper clippings on subjects ranging from veterans issues and the Groton submarine base, to Six Flags and tourism in Connecticut as well as files concerning the recognition of Connecticut's Native Americans. Gejdenson's papers also include press releases concerning the environment, Electric Boat, and the Soviet Union's treatment of Jews.
Also among the papers are administrative records from Congress, foreign relation materials, and defense files. Issues related to the environment, Native Americans, animal rights, transportation, and nuclear energy are also featured within the collection. While focused primarily on the issues that Gejdenson dealt with during his time in office the papers also feature more private details of Gejdenson's life such as his daily schedule for various periods of time while a U.S. Representative, his House journals, travel records, and campaign speeches and documents.
While the majority of the the collection is in print form, Gejdenson took great efforts to modernize his own record keeping and documentation files and as a result there is a good portion of the collection on now outdated forms of technology including floopy disks and various forms of audio and videocassettes.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged and described as shelved.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open and available for research except for those constituent related files awaiting individual review to protect personal privacy.
Acquisition Information
The papers were donated by United States Congressman Sam Gejdenson in 2000.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to Connecticut politics. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the Reading Room desk.
Administrative records.; Audio cassettes.; Audio visual materials.; Correspondence.; Financial Records.; Fliers. [printed matter]; Minutes.; Newsletters.; Newspapers.; Notes.; Photocopies.; Photographs.; Political Collections; Politician.; Press releases.; Publications.; Resolutions.; Speeches.; Videocassettes.
- Series I: An Inventory, undated, 1966-2001
  - Press Clippings, correspondence, undated, 1996-1998 (Box 1)
    - Education Vochures, undated, 1997-1998
    - Pensions, undated, 1997-1998
    - American Heritage River, undated, 1997
    - Agriculture, undated, 1997
    - Banking, undated, 1997 February- September
    - Base Closing, 1997 June 6
    - Budget, undated, 1997-1998
    - Business, undated, 1996 December- 1997
    - Campaign Finance, undated, 1997
    - Cereral, Undated, 1997 July 4
    - Defense, undated, 1996 December - 1997
    - Economy, undated, 1996 December - 1997
    - Education, undated, 1997
    - Election 1998, undated, 1998
    - Electric Boat, undated, 1996 December - 1997 November
    - Environment, undated, 1996 December - 1997 September
    - Foreign Policy, undated, 1997 May
    - Miscellaneous, undated, 1997-1998
    - Gambling, undated, 1997 February- September
    - Health Care, undated, 1996 December - 1997 October
    - Housing, undated, 1996 December - 1997
    - Jobs, undated, 1996 December - 1997 March
    - Labor, undated, 1996 December - 1997 October
    - Local Politics, undated, 1997-1998
    - Millstone, undated, 1996 October - 1997 October
    - Mashantucket Pequots, undated, 1997-1998
    - New London, CT, undated, 1996 December - 1997 June
    - NUWC/NUSC, undated, 1996 December - 1997 June
    - Police, undated, 1996 December - 1997 September
    - Nuclear, 1997-1998
    - John Rowland, undated, 1996 December - 1997 March
    - Seawolf, undated, 1997 April - June
    - Six Flags, undated, 1997 Feburary - June
    - Submarine Base, undated, 1996 December - 1997 September
    - Taxes, undated
    - Tourism, 1997
    - Trade, undated, 1996 June
    - Transportation, undated, 1996 December - 1997 October
    - University of Connecticut, undated, 1997 September - October
    - Veterans, undated, 1997 April - May
    - Voting Record, undated, 1997 March - April
    - Welfare, undated, 1996 December - 1997
    - Gejdenson Clips, undated, 1996 December - 1998
    - Letters to the Editors, undated, 1996 December - 1997
    - Newletters, undated, 1998
    - NASA Press Release, undated, 1998
    - Constituent correspondence, undated, 1998
    - Electric Boat, undated, 1996 December - 1997 November
    - Pratt & Whitney, undated, 1997-1998
    - Mohegans, undated, 1997-1998
  - Transportation, undated, 1988-1998 (Box 2)
    - Route 6, undated, 1994-1997
    - Amtrak, undated
    - Intermodal Surface Transportation Efficency Act, ISTEA, undated, 1988-1991
    - Route 2, undated, 1994-1997
  - Press Releases, undated, 1981, 1986 (Box 3)
    - Enviroment, undated, 1986
    - Health, undated, 1986
    - Electric Boat, undated, 1981
    - Reagan, undated, 1981
  - Press Clippings, undated,1997 June - 1998 April (Box 4)
    - Press Clippings, undated
    - Agriculture, undated 1997-1998
    - Banking, undated, 1997-1998
    - Cereal, undated, 1997-1998
    - Environment, undated, 1997-1998
    - Energy, undated, 1997-1998
    - Education, undated, 1997-1998
    - Gambling, undated, 1997-1998
    - Mashantucket Pequots, undated, 1997-1998
    - Mohegans, undated, 1997-1998
    - General files, undated, 1997-1998
    - Transportation, undated, 1997-1998
    - Local Politics, undated, 1997-1998
    - Local Issues, undated, 1997-1998
    - Electric Boat, undated, 1997-1998
  - Press Releases, undated, 1982-1983 (Box 5)
    - Firefighters, undated, 1982
    - Soviet Union treatment of Jews, yndated, 1982
    - Opposition in 1982 election, undated, 1982
    - Native Americans, undated, 1983
    - Environment, undated, 1983
  - Energy, undated, 1991-2000 (Box 6)
    - Coal, undated
    - Nuclear, undated
  - Administrative Records, undated, 1997-2000 (Box 7)
    - Briefing Books, 105th and 106th Congress, undated, 1997-2000
    - Floor statements, 105th Congress, undated, 1997
    - Legislative Profile, 105th and 106th Congress, undated, 1997-2000
    - Sponsored and Cosponsored Bills, 106th Congress, undated, 1998-2000
  - Foreign Relations, undated, 1986-1992 (Box 8)
    - South America, undated, 1988-1992
    - Caribbean, undated, 1988-1992
    - Human Rights, undated, 1988-1992
    - Narcotics, undated
    - Iran-Contra, undated, 1986-1990
    - Haiti, undated, 1988-1992
  - Energy, Native Americans, and Administrative Records, undated, 1981-1994 (Box 9)
    - Appliance and Light Bulb Efficancy, undated, 1985-1992
    - Alaska n Drilling, undated, 1985-1992
    - Mic Mac Recongition, undated, 1985
    - Native American Burial Ground, undated, 1989
    - Legislative Profile, undated, 1981-1994
    - Briefing Books, undated
    - Legislative Accomplishment, undated
  - Press Releases, undated, 1983 - 1984 (Box 10)
    - Springfield Sewage, 1983
    - Population, 1983
    - Notch Year Benefits, 1983
    - Medicaid/Medicare, 1983
    - Family History, 1983
    - Social Security, 1983
    - Radio Marti, 1983
    - Ocean Issues, undated, 1983
    - Nuclear Waste, 1983
    - Indian Settlement, 1983
    - Gejdenson Bill, 1983
    - GAO Report on Connecticut Flood, 1983
    - Gound Water Contamination, 1983
    - Radio Spot for Putnam, 1984
    - Salvador Certification Lawsuit, 1984
    - Japan, 1983
    - Pratt & Whitney Contracts, 1984
    - Town Meetings, 1984
    - Home Base Conference, 1984
    - New Hampshire Primary Dinner, 1984
    - Eastern Connecticut Cable Program, 1984
    - Exports, 1984
    - Human Rights Aid to El Salvador, 1984
    - Coast Guard Oversight, 1984
    - Connecticut/ Rhode Island Delegations' letter to Lewis, 1984
    - Submarine Base, 1984
    - Small Business Adminstration, 1984
    - Hunger, 1984
    - General Dynamics, 1984
    - Water Resource Center, 1984
    - Food for Peace, 1984
    - New England Environmental Priorities, 1984
    - School Lunch, 1984
    - Energy, 1984
    - Gejdenson's Biography, 1984
    - Foreign Aid, 1984
    - Financial Disclosure, 1984
    - New Ireland Forum, 1984
    - Veterans' Center, 1984
    - Floods, 1984
    - Arts, 1984
    - Military Construction, 1984
    - Equal Pay Act, 1984
    - American Thread Company, 1984
    - InterRoyal, 1984
    - Indian Health Care, 1984
    - Education, 1984
    - Older Americans, 1984
    - Child Restraints, 1984
  - Veterans' affairs, Postal Stamps, undated, 1990-2000 (Box 11)
    - Veterans' Health Care, undated, 1998-2000
    - Veterans' Affairs Office, undated, 1990-2000
    - Submarine Stamp, undated, 1998-2000
    - Postal Service, undated, 1997-2000
  - Pensions and Energi-Lite, undated, 1995-2000 (Box 12)
    - Energi-Lite Regulations, undated, 1997-2000
    - Pensions, undated, 1995-1998
    - House Resolution 4152, undated
    - Samers' Report, 1998
    - OWL Event, undated, 1998
    - Women and Pensions, undated, 1997-1998
  - Pensions and Small Business Adminstration, undated, 1989-2000 (Box 13)
    - Small Business Outreach, undated, 2000
    - Retirement Planning Conference, undated, 2000
    - Employee Stock Ownership Plan, undated, 1999-2000
    - S. Corporate Loan, undated, 1999-2000
    - Individual Retirement Account, undated, 2000
    - Pension Legislation, undated, 1999-2000
    - Small Business Association, Microloan Program, undated, 1996-1998
    - Small Business Regulation Relief Act, 1996-1997
    - Business, undated, 1992-1997
    - Small Business Association, undated, 1997
    - National Funeral Directors Association, undated, 1998
    - Merchant Fleet, undated, 2000
    - Volunteer Firefighter Tax, undated, 1997-2000
  - Defense Files, undated, 1980-1990 (Box 14)
    - General Dynamics, undated, 1980-1990
    - Electic Boat, undated, 1980-1990
    - Naval Contracts, undated
    - General Dynamics/ Electic Boat Probe, undated, 1986-1989
    - Submarines, undated, 1980-1990
    - Defense Budget, undated, 1985-1987
  - Administrative Records, undated, 1994-2001 (Box 15)
    - Route 6 Environmental Impact Statements, undated, 1994-1995
    - Electrification Environmental Impact Statements, undated, 1994
    - Research Book one and two, undated, 1995-1996
    - Solomon Reserve Officer Training Corps, undated, 1997-1998
    - Connecticut Department of Transportation, undated, 1999-2000
    - Gejdenson Biography and offical portrait, undated, 1999-2001
    - 106th Congress Form Letters (Floppy Disks), undated, 1999-2001
  - Cereal Price Investigation, Undated, 1993-1998 (Box 16)
    - Cereal, undated, 1993-1997
    - Cereal Reports, undated, 1996
    - Newspaper Clippings, undated, 1994-1998
    - Cotterill Information, undated, 1993-1997
    - Cereal Price Increases, undated, 1997
    - Anti-Trust letter to Janet Reno, undated, 1995
    - Alfred E. Kahn, undated, 1996
    - Cotterill Award, undated, 1997
    - Cereal Coupons, undated, 1996
    - General Mills/ Ralcorp Merger, undated, 1997
    - Cereal Store Prices, undated, 1996-1997
    - New York Court Case regarding Cereal, undated, 1994
  - Gejdenson's legislative profile, undated, 1997-2001 (Box 17)
    - Gejdenson's Sponsored Legislation, 106th Congress, undated, 1999-2001
    - Communication Regarding Legislation, undated, 1999-2001
    - Letters of Support, undated, 1999-2001
    - Newspaper Clippings, undated, 1999-2001
    - Legislation's effect on Connecticut, undated, 1999-20001
    - Gejdenson's Sponsored Legislation, 105th Congress, undated, 1997-1999
  - Admistrative Records and Press Clippings, undated, 1991-1998 (Box 18)
    - Gejdenson's Co-sponsored Legislation, 104th Congress, undated, 1995-1997
    - Gejdenson's Co-Sponsored Legislation, 105th Congress, undated, 1997-1998
    - Gejdenson's Co-signed Letters, 104th Congress, undated, 1995-1997
    - Gejdenson's Co-signed Letters, 105th Congress, undated, 1997-1998
    - District Issues, undated, 1997
    - Voting Records, undated, 1996-1997
    - Floor Remarks, undated, 1996-1997
    - Amendments, undated, 1996-1997
    - Student Loans, undated, 1991-1992
    - Naval Underwater Systems Center, Press Clippings, undated, 1991
    - Base Closings, Press Clippings, undated, 1991
  - Videocassette Tapes, undated, 1985 February - April (Box 19)
    - Sam Fishing "Good" (1), undated
    - Unlabeled (4), undated
    - Messages from Gejdenson (6), 1985 February - April
  - Defense Files, undated, 1985-1995 (Box 20)
    - Groton Submaire Base, undated, 1991-1995
    - Defense Budget, undated, 1985-1988
    - Military Construction (MILCON), undated, 1985-1988
    - Naval Underwater Warfare Ceter, undated
    - Base Closure and Realignment Comimission (BRAC), undated, 1991-1995
  - Multimedia, undated, 1980-1990 (Box 21)
    - Bob Steele (1 Reel), 1981 Fall
    - Blank (1), undated
    - First Presidential Debate (1), 1988
    - Advertisements (1), undated
    - Gejdenson in Congress (5), undated
    - Clips of the News (2), undated
    - 176 Audio Recording Tapes (3), undated
    - Unlabeled Audio Cassettes (6), undated
    - Audio Cassettes of Media Clips (8), 1986-1988
    - Audio Cassettes from Conferences (4), 1986
    - Unidentified Audio Cassettes (4), 1982
    - Gejdenson's Political Position Audio Cassettes (22), undated, 1985-1990
    - Campaign Audio Cassettes (6), undated, 1980-1988
  - District Issues, Military, 1991-1996 (Box 22)
    - State Pier, undated, 1992-1994
    - New Attack Submarine, NAS, undated, 1992-1994
    - Base Closure and Reallignment Commission (BRAC), 1991-1996
    - Groton Realignment, undated, 1991-1995
    - Airport, undated
    - Fuel Cells, undated, 1992-1994
  - Miltary Issues, 1993-1995 (Box 23)
    - Base Closure and Realignment Commission (BRAC) Reports and Testimony, 1993-1995
    - Seawolf Homebasing Enviromental Impact Statement, 1995
  - Videocassettes, undated, 1985-1986 (Box 24)
    - Unlabeled (9), undated
    - CBS News, Gejdenson's Haiti Trip (1), 1986 April 4
    - Pasadena Launch Footage unedited (1), 1987 September 12
  - Legislative Material, 1977-1996 (Box 25)
    - Consumer Protection, undated
    - Health Care, undated, 1994
    - Electrfication, undated
    - Airport, undated, 1992-1995
    - Intermodal Surface Transportation Efficiency Act (ISTEA), undated, 1991
    - Transportation, unidentified Cases, undated, 1991-1995
  - Agriculture, Roger Dumas, undated, 1987-2000 (Box 26)
    - North East Dairy Compact, undated, 1996-1997
    - Meat Legislation, undated, 1994
    - University of Connecticut Argicultural Programs, undated, 1992-2000
    - Women, Infant, and Children (WIC) Program's Fram Stand Coupons, undated, 1992-2000
    - Fisheries, Summer Flounder, undated, 1996-1997
    - Roger Dumas, 1979-1988
  - Legislative Issues, undated, 1982-1992 (Box 27)
    - European Trade '92, undated, 1992
    - Taxes, undated, 1985-1989
  - Military Issues, undated, 1989-1994 (Box 28)
    - Seawolf Files, undated, 1989-1994
    - Electic Boat and Jobs, undated, 1991-1994
    - Base Closure and Realignment Commission (BRAC) I and II, undated, 1991-1994
    - Electic Boat Press Clippings, undated
    - Naval Underwater Systems Center, undated, 1991-1994
  - Press Clippings, Press Releases, and Speeches, undated, 1982-1988 (Box 29)
    - Press Releases, undated, 1986-1987
    - Speeches, undated, 1986-1987
    - Press Clippings, undated, 1987-1988
    - Reelection Press, undated, 1982-1983
    - Economy Press, undated, 1982-1983
    - General Press, undated, 1982-1983
    - Women, Infants, and Children (WIC) Farmers' Market, 1988 Feburary 4
    - Drugs at Seabrook, 1987 January 28
    - Fire Roberts, 1988 January 12
    - Education Boards, 1988 January 5, 7
    - Trident, 1988 January 5
    - Nuclear Terrorism, 1988 March 8
    - Archeological Report, 1988 February 25
    - Delay JVA Plant Start, 1988 February 19
    - Vietam Veterans, Women, 1988 June 22
    - Nuclear Reglatory Commission Report, 1987 December 27
    - Handicapped Parking Report, 1987 March 14
    - Tongass Hearing, 1987 January 29
    - Archives Records Information Access System (ARIAS) Plan Amendment, 1987 December 8
    - Bialy Letter, 1987 December 4
    - Trident Colloquy, 1987 January 23
    - Ground Water, 1987 December 2
    - Housing Conference, 1987 November 16
    - Water Waste, 1988 April 7
  - Campaign Finance Reform, undated, 1995-1998 (Box 30)
    - Legislation, undated, 1995-1998
    - Committee Testimony, undated, 1995-1998
    - Dear Collegue Letters, undated, 1995-1998
    - Congressional Correspondence, undated, 1995-1998
    - Letters from Organizations, undated, 1995-1998
    - Press Clippings, undated, 1995-1998
    - Briefing Books, undated, 1995-1998
  - Foreign Affairs, undated, 1980-1989 (Box 31)
    - Travel Plans and Itineraries, undated, 1983-1987
    - Promotional Materials about Counties, undated, 1980-1989
    - Foriegn Affairs Legislation, undated, 1983-1987
    - Correspondence between Foreign Countries and Congress, undated, 1980-1989
    - Press Clippings, undated, 1983-1987
  - Foreign Affairs, undated, 1988-1992 (Box 32)
    - Appropriations, Fiscal Year 1992, undated, 1991
    - Somalia, undated, 1988-1992
    - South Africa, undated, 1988
    - Export Legislation, undated, 1990
    - Foreign Policy Legislation, undated, 1988-1992
    - Correspondence, undated, 1988-1992
    - Reports, undated, 1988-1992
    - Testimony, undated, 1988-1992
  - Videocassettes and Press, undated, 1982-1996 (Box 33)
    - Unlabeled (7), undated
    - Television Spots (),3, undated
    - Campaign (1), undated
    - Gejdenson on the Floor (5), undated, 1982-1996
    - Educational Videos about Congress, undated, 1982-1996
    - Press Clippings, undated, 1988-1992
    - Press Releases, undated, 1988-1992
  - Gejdenson's Schedule and House Journals, 1983-1996 (Box 34)
    - Gejdenson's Schedule, Bulk, 1983-1986; 1983- 1986 February, 1996
    - House Journal, 99th Congress, Second Session, Part 2, 1986
  - Energy Files, undated, 1980-1999 (Box 35)
    - Millstone, undated, 1994-1999
    - Northeast Utilities, undated, 1994-1999
    - Nuclear Reglatory Commission Investigation, undated, 1994-1999
    - Background Documents on Engery, undated, 1980, 1987
    - Correspondence between Gejdenson, Nuclear Reglatory Commission and Northeast Utilities, undated, 1994-1999
    - Press Clippings, undated, 1994-1999
    - Reports, undated, 1994-1999
    - Lawsuits, undated, 1994-1999
  - Energy and Diversification, undated, 1985-1991 (Box 36)
    - Nuclear Power, undated, 1989-1990
    - Diversification, undated, 1985-1991
    - Alternative Energy, undated, 1989-1991
    - Utility and Business, undated, 1989-1991
    - Labor, undated, 1989-1991
  - District Issues, undated, 1983-1991 (Box 37)
    - District Information Press Clippings, undated, 1983-1991
    - Congressional Witness Legislation, undated, 1988-1991
    - Town Meetings, undated, 1988
    - Census (1980 and 1990), undated, 1983-1991
  - Admistrative Records, undated, 1981-1997 (Box 38)
    - Briefing Books, undated, 1992-1994
    - Legislation, undated, 1981-1994
    - Legislative Accomplishments, 102nd and 103rd Congresses, undated, 1991-1993
    - Congressional Pay Raises, undated, 1988-1990
    - Co-signed Letters, undated, 1989-1990
    - Thank You Notes, undated, 1981-1984
    - Constituent Concerns on Taxes, undated, 1989
    - Veterans, undated, 1989-1990
    - Economy, undated, 1994-1996
    - Labor and Wages, undated, 1994-1996
    - Population, undated, 1991-1997
    - Labor Robo Letters, undated, 1991-1997
  - Foreign Trade, undated, 1988-1992 (Box 39)
    - Iraq, undated, 1990-1992
    - Micro-Enterprise, undated, 1988-1990
    - Missle Technology, undated, 1989-1990
    - North American Fair Trade Agreement (NAFTA), undated, 1989-1991
    - Overseas Private Investiment Coporation (OPIC) and PRE, undated, 1990-1991
    - South Africa n Sanctions, undated, 1991
    - Textiles, undated, 1990-1992
    - Tied Aid, undated, 1989-1991
    - Trade and Development Program, undated, 1991
    - U.S. and Foriegn Commerical Service, undated, 1990
    - Center for World Trade, undated, 1989
    - Japan, undated, 1989-1991
    - Jackson/Vanik, undated, 1989-1990
    - Trade (General), undated, 1988-1992